Mss.Rec.12 Mss.Rec.12
American Philosophical Society
Northern Tepehuan language material
1951, 1956, 1958
Mss.Rec.12
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Tape(s)
Northern Tepehuan songs and stories originally recorded on wire by John Alden Mason in 1951, 1956, and 1958 Numerous short songs, folkloric and unidentified stories, description of pottery-making, conversation in Spanish on indigenous peoples, and texts and speech in the Macoba dialect of Pima Bajo. Recorded in Baborigame (Chihuahua,) Hermosillo, and Onavas (Sonora.) Tepehuan consultants are Gerónimo Aguilar, Andrés Carrillo, Antonio Carrillo, Celestina Carrillo, Dolores Carrillo, Juan Carrillo, Lorenzo Carrillo, Carolina Chaparro de Carrillo, Catalina Carrillo De Onteveros, Dolores Molina, and Julio Estrella. The Pima Bajo consultant is Nacho Lucero Coyote. Some material was recorded by David M. Brugge or Burton Bascom.
3 sound tape reels (2 hr., 9 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1 track, mono; 5 in.
Bascom, Burton W.
Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by John A. Mason, 1952.
Biographical/Historical note
John Alden Mason was an anthropologist and archaeologist.
Scope and Contents
Tape 1. Duplicate of speech and songs of the Northern Tepehuan language, made from the original wire spool recorded at Baborigame, Chihuahua, Mexico, March 1951, by John Alden Mason of the University Museum, University of Pennsylvania. Duplicates from the original wire spool were made on 6 July 1951 by John Alden Mason and Leigh Lisker.
Tape 2. Continuation of tape 1. Recorded March-April 1951. Prominent background hum partially corrected at -12dB at 630hz during transfer to RDAT.
Tape 3. Continuation of tape 2. Elicitaton of Northern Tepehuan given in Spanish by Burton Bascom. The subsequent material on the tape was recorded at 15 ips and not transferred to RDAT with other programs. The portion not transferred to RDAT is a duplicate of the preceding program.
Tape 4. Northern Tepehuan speech and song. Tape duplicate of wire spool made in April 1951 at Baborigame, Chihuahua, Mexico. Tape duplicate made at the Univeristy Museum, University of Pennsylvania on 1 July 1954. Prominent line hum.
Tape 5. Lower Pima (Pima Bajo) texts. Dialect of Macoba (Sonora-Chihuahua border.) Recorded by David Brugge in Hermosillo, Sonora, June 1958, with consultant Nacho Lucero Coyote and interpreter Lorenzo Jimenez. Correspondence between Brugge and Mason regarding this research trip can be found in the John Alden Mason papers.
Tape 6. Lower Pima (Pima Bajo) material recorded at Onavas, Sonora, Mexico by David Brugge. Received by Mason from Brugge in June 1956. Poor sound quality overall due to oocilation on original wire recording.
Accruals note
This collection is separated into two parts: tapes 1-3, which were the collector's original tapes contained in this collection, and tapes 4-6, which were removed from the collector's papers in the APS Library and added to this collection in July of 1989. The recordings in the APS Library are duplicates made from the collector's original wire spools.
Indians of Mexico--Languages; Sound recordings; Tepehuan language
- Audio recordings
  - Northern Tepehuan speech, 1951-03-17; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:59; Aguilar, Gerónimo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Wire recording) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan language
  - The Story of Bear and Cricket, 1951-03-18; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:10; Aguilar, Gerónimo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Scope and Contents note
    Story in Northern Tepehuan.
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Bears--Folklore; Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan language
  - The Story of the Shingle Maker, 1951-03-21; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:10; Aguilar, Gerónimo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan Indians--Social life and customs; Tepehuan language
  - The Story of the Bear and the Planter, 1951-03-21; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:03; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - Description of pottery-making and other household activities, 1951-03-26; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:13; De Carrillo, Catalina Chaparro; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Pottery craft; Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Social life and customs; Tepehuan language
  - The Story of the Pig and the Burro, 1951-03; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:31; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Swine--Folklore; Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan language
  - A Tepehuan Song about the Moon, 1951-03; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:23; Carrillo, Antonio; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan Indians--Music; Tepehuan language
  - The Song of the Chipmunk, 1951-03; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:27; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Song in Northern Tepehuan.
  - The Bonanza Song, 1951-03; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:21; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Little Owl, 1951-03; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:44; Carrillo, Dolores; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Burro, 1951-03; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:18; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Calandria, 1951-03; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:33; Carrillo, Dolores; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Piñon Tree, 1951-03; 01-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:27; Carrillo, Dolores; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Dawn, 1951-03; 01-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:21; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of Baborigame, 1951-03; 01-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:53; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Ants, 1951-03; 01-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:51; Carrillo, Antonio; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of Jesus Encinas, 1951-03; 01-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; de Carrillo, Carolina Chaparro; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Mischevious Boy, 1951-03; 01-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:32; Carrillo, Celestina; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - La canción del chiquito, 1951-03; 01-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:27; de Carrillo, Carolina Chaparro; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Story of the Mountain Lion, 1951-03-27; 01-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:28; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Puma--Folklore; Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan language
  - The Song of the Pig, 1951-03-27; 01-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:26; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Journey of Don Sotiero Ramírez, 1951-03-27; 01-22; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:55; Carrillo, Andrés; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan language
  - The Story of the Hunter, 1951-03-27; 01-23; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:29; Carrillo, Lorenzo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967; Molina, Dolores
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Hunters--Folklore; Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan language
  - The Story of Eagle and Coyote, 1951-03-27; 01-24; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:56; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Eagles--Folklore; Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan Indians; Tepehuan Indians--Folklore; Tepehuan language
  - The Song of the Town of Cinco Llagas, 1951-03-27; 01-25; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:28; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Rancho Curave, 1951-03-27; 01-26; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:22; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Song of the Little One, 1951-03-27; 01-27; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:46; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967; Molina, Dolores
  - The Story of the Rabbit, or the Tar Baby Story, 1951-03-27; 01-28; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:37; Carrillo, Andrés; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - Northern Tepehuan speech, 1951-04; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:13; Carrillo, Andrés; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Tale of the Peanut, 1951-04; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:50; Carrillo, Andrés; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - The Story of the Poor Man with Many Children, 1951-04-03; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:25; De Onteveros, Catalina Carrillo; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
  - Some examples of Northern Tepehuan phonetics and morphology, 1951-05; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:29; Bascom, Burton William, 1921-; Carrillo, Juan; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967
    Elicitaitions given in Spanish to a Northern Tepehuan speaker.
    Baborigame (Chihuahua, Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Tepehuan language--Morphology; Tepehuan language--Phonetics
  - Pima Bajo Text No. 2, 1958-06; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:48; Brugge, David M.; Coyote, Nacho Lucero; Jimenez, Lorenzo
    Spanish translation of a text in Pima Bajo. Pima Bajo language, dialect of Macoba (Sonora-Chihuahua border)
    Hermosillo (Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Pima Bajo language
  - Pima Bajo text, 1958-06; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:56; Brugge, David M.; Coyote, Nacho Lucero
    Pima Bajo language, dialect of Macoba (Sonora-Chihuahua border)
    Hermosillo (Mexico); Indians of Mexico--Chihuahua (State); Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Pima Bajo language
  - Pima Bajo Text No. 4, 1958-06; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:38; Brugge, David M.; Coyote, Nacho Lucero
  - Conversation in Pima Bajo and Spanish, 1958-06; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:42; Brugge, David M.; Coyote, Nacho Lucero; Jimenez, Lorenzo
    Lower Pima (Pima Bajo) texts. Dialect of Macoba (Sonora-Chihuahua border).
  - Pima Bajo text, 1958-06; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:58; Brugge, David M.; Coyote, Nacho Lucero; Jimenez, Lorenzo
  - Pima Bajo text, 1958-06; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:27; Brugge, David M.; Coyote, Nacho Lucero
    Pima Bajo language, dialect of Macoba (Sonora-Chihuahua border).
  - Discussion in Spanish about indigenous people, 1956-06; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:03; Brugge, David M.; Estrella, Julio
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language
  - Pima Bajo speech, 1956-06; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:54; Brugge, David M.
    No speaker identification available in documentation.
  - Spanish song, 1956-06; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:11; Brugge, David M.
    No identification of singers given in existing documentation.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State)--Music; Onavas (Sonora, Mexico)